<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the preventing of the multiplicity of buildings in and about the suburbs of London, and vvithin ten miles thereof. At the Parliament begun at Westminster the 17th day of September, an. Dom. 1656.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82458</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859385</idno>
  <idno type="VID">111460</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240884351</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1065_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859385</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99859385e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 159:E1065[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the preventing of the multiplicity of buildings in and about the suburbs of London, and vvithin ten miles thereof. At the Parliament begun at Westminster the 17th day of September, an. Dom. 1656.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills and Iohn Field, Printers to His Highness the Lord Protector,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>On A2r: last word in first line of text: 'Excessive'; first word under initial: 'and'; last word in last full line of text: 'of'.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Building laws --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">London (England) --  Buildings, structures, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111460:1"/>
            <fw>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </fw>
            <p>AN ACT FOR THE Preventing of the Multiplicity of BUILDINGS In and about the Suburbs of LONDON, AND VVithin Ten Miles thereof. At the Parliament begun at Westminster the 17<seg rend="sup">th</seg> day of September, An. Dom. 1656.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the Protectorate.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by Henry Hills and Iohn Field, Printers to His Highness the Lord PROTECTOR. 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111460:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111460:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT FOR THE Preventing of the Multiplicity of BUILDINGS In and about the Suburbs of LONDON, AND VVithin Ten Miles thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Great and Excessive Number of Houses, Edifices, Out-houses and Cottages erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and new built in and about the Suburbs of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the parts thereunto adjoyning, is found to be very mischievous and inconvenient, and a great Annoyance and Nusance to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; And whereas notwithstanding divers Prohibitions heretofore had and made to the contrary, yet the said growing Evil is of late so much multiplied and increased, that there is a necessity of taking some further and speedy Course for the Redress thereof: And whereas by the Law the said Houses and Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sances ought to be abated, and the Builders, Occupiers, Continuers and Tenants thereof ought to make Fines for the same; so that if the Severity of the Law should be inflicted in such Cases, it would tend to the undoing of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111460:3"/> divers persons who have laid out all, or a great part of their Estates in such new Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: For the Reformation therefore of the aforesaid Mischief and Nusance for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and the prevention of the like for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and for the avoiding of Suits, Present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Indictments which are, and may otherwise be brought and had against such Builders, Owners and Tenants of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Houses, Edifices, Out-houses and Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages so built and continued as aforesaid; Be it Enacted and Ordained by His Highness the Lord Protector and this present Parliament, and by the Authority thereof, That for every Dwelling-house, Out-house, or any other Building erected, built and continued upon any new Foundation within the Suburbs of the said City of <hi>London,</hi> or in any other place or places within Ten Miles of the Walls of the said City, since the Twenty fifth day of <hi>March</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty, and not having four Acres of Land at least, according to the Statute or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance <hi>De Terris mensurandis,</hi> being his or her Free-hold and Inheritance that have so built, continually therewith used, occupied and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, there shall be paid unto His Highness the Lord Protector, or to His Successors, for the use of the Commonwealth, one Years Rent or Years Value, at the full and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved yearly value of every such Dwelling-house, Out-house and other Building; which said improved Value or Rent, shall be paid by the immediate Tenant or Tenants, Occupier or Occupiers of such Houses at a Rack-rent, and he or they to be reimbursed the same out
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111460:3"/> of the Rents or Profits of such Houses, Any Covenant, Promise, Contract or Security made or given by such Tenants or Occupiers to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And in case the said Houses are not held at a Rack-rent, then the said years Rent or Value shall be divided and severally assessed upon, and paid by the Owners and Tenants thereof in such proportion as to the Commissioners to be appointed for that purpose, or any three or more of them shall seem meet, always having due regard to the quantity, quality and value of the several and respective Interests and Estates therein, whose Determination and Settlement thereof shall be a full and final Conclusion to the said immediate Tenant or Tenants and Proprietors, and to all parties therein concerned; which said years value or profit shall be paid in full Satisfaction and Discharge of all and every such Fine or Fines, Forfeiture or Forfeitures, Penalty or Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as such person or persons, Tenant or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants were or are lyable to lose or pay for the building or continuing of such Houses, and such Builders, Owners, Tenants and Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof, and every of them, from and after such payment, by the Authority aforesaid, shall be for ever hereafter acquitted, exonerated and discharged of and from such Fine, Penalty or Forfeiture; which said Years Rent or Value shall be paid in maner and form following; (That is to say) One Moyety upon the Nine and twentieth day of <hi>September,</hi> One thousand six hundred fifty and seven, or within Three Moneths after the setting of the said Fine, and the other Moyety upon the Twenty fifth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111460:4"/> day of <hi>March</hi> then next following, or within six moneths after the setting of the said Fine.</p>
            <p>And to the intent that the said years Rent may be Assessed, Levied, and Raised Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably and Indifferently upon every Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Tenant, and Vnder-tenant respectively, of every such Dwelling-house, Out-house and new Building, according to their several E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states and Interests therein, And for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Discovery of the said new built Houses, and Edifices, and for the more speedy levying of the aforesaid Values and Rents of the said respective Houses &amp; Edifices so built and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued as aforesaid; Be it Enacted and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Authority aforesaid, That a Commission shall be made and directed by the Commissioners of the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> unto such fit Persons as His Highness the Lord Protector shall nominate, not exceeding the number of fifteen; and likewise to a fit Person to be a Receiver of such Moneys as shall be Assessed by vertue of this Act, and to three able and fit Persons to be Registers to do as it shall be hereafter in this Act directed and appointed: And the Commissioners so Constituted, or any three or more of them are hereby required, on or by the first day of <hi>July,</hi> 1657. to direct their several or joynt Precept or Precepts to such Inhabitants, Constables, Sub-Constables, Bailiffs, Tythingmen, and other like Officers of the respective Parishes, Places, and Counties within the Suburbs of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and within ten miles of the aforesaid City of <hi>London,</hi> or to so many of them, or such other Person or Persons as they shall think fitting, requiring them and every
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111460:4"/> of them to make Certificates fairly Written of the several Houses, Edifices, Out-Houses, and Cottages within the respective Parishes, Tythings, and Places, in which they dwell or are appointed to inquire, as have been built and continued since the five and twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> in the year of our Lord one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred and twenty, not having four Acres of Land belonging to them as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, and of the true yearly improved Value thereof, and the Names of such as built the same, and in whose Possession, Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, and Tenure they now are, and what Estate they have therein, and who are Owners of the Inheritance thereof, and of the Place of their respective Habitations and Professions; of which said Warrants and the Contents thereof, they shall leave notice in Writing at the dwelling place, with the Owner or Occupier of every dwelling House in the respective Parishes within y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Places and Counties aforesaid: And the Tenants, Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers, &amp; Owners of the said Houses are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by required, at some convenient place by the said Persons therein imployed appointed for their meeting, to certifie &amp; inform the said per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons accordingly; which said Certificates they y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Persons so imployed shall deliver to the Commissioners, or any three or more of them, who shall cause y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Certificates so returned, to be filed by the Register or Registers, &amp; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on consideration thereof by them had, equally impose and ascertain the respective sum or sums to be charged upon the Tenant, Owner, or Occupier of such new erected Buildings, Out-houses, or Edifices respectively; which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111460:5"/> said Sum or Sums so charged and ascertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, shall be fairly written and entred in a Book to be provided for that purpose by the Register or Registers to be appointed as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, and a Transcript thereof fairly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Parchment, shall be by him and them delivered in to the Barons of his Highness Court of Exchequer, in the same Court to be filed and remain upon Record; And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, or any three or more of them, after such Entry and Transcript made and Record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as aforesaid, shall issue out Warrants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Hands and Seal, to such person and persons as they or any three or more of them shall appoint, to Summon the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Tenants Owners and Occupiers so charged, to pay in the several and respective Sums assessed upon them, to the Receiver authorized and appointed as aforesaid, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such day and days as the Commissioners or any three or more of them shall appoint, according to the times in this Act li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited. And the said Commissioners or any three or more of them, shall have power to issue out their Warrant or Warrants, under their Hands and Seals, unto the said Receiver, to pay unto the said Commissioners and every of them, all such Sum and Sums of Money as shall grow due unto them from time to time for their Salaries, according to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances and Limitations in this Act hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prescribed, as also all other Sum and Sums of Money as shall grow due for the Salaries of the Receiver, Register, or any the Officers imployed in the Execution of this Act; And for all other contingent Charges
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111460:5"/> expended in the necessary carrying on of the Service; And the said Receiver is hereby Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized, upon the receipt of the said Warrant or Warrants, to issue and pay out the said re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Sums accordingly, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all the several Sums of Money by him received, he the said Receiver shall, and is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by required to pay the same within seven days after the receipt thereof (into his custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) into the Receipt of his Highness Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; And in case the said Commissioners, or any three or more of them, in their several and respective Limits, shall have information, knowledge, or just cause of suspicion, that any Houses, Edifices, Out-houses or Cottages, so new built or continued as aforesaid, are omitted or left out of the Certificates so to be delivered to them as aforesaid, or that any such houses comprized in the said Certificates are undervalued, or the Names of the Owners or Tenants thereof, or Estates therein concealed, That then the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, or any three or more of them (after discovery thereof, either by Inquiry by Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or by examination of any Witnesses upon Oath or otherwise; which said Oath the said Commissioners or any three or more of them, are hereby Impowered to administer and give to the said Iury and Witnesses) shall insert the number of such Houses and Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Names of the Owners and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants thereof, and their Estates therein, with the places of their Habitation and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession so omitted in the said Certificates, and Rate such Houses and Edifices as shall be so undervalued, or were omitted therein, at the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111460:6"/> true yearly Value or Rack-Rent thereof, and shall have power to send for such person or persons as they shall conceive requisite to inform them in the premises as aforesaid; And in case of refusal of any person or persons to appear before them, or to discover the truth in the Premises upon Oath or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise as aforesaid, they shall and have power hereby given them to Fine such person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, so as the Fine to be imposed on any such person exceed not the sum of ten pounds for every such offence: And all Sheriffs, under-Sheriffs, and other their Officers, are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by required to be aiding, assisting, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the said Commissioners, or any of them, for the returning of Iuries or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, in the execution of this Act; and after such Certificates so made and rectified by them as aforesaid, the said Commissioners or any three or more of them, are hereby required to make two true Copies or parts thereof, fairly written in Parchment under their Hands and Seals, and forthwith to certifie one part thereof with the aforesaid Fines and Forfeitures so to be imposed, into his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness Court of Exchequer, to the intent that the same may be and remain a Charge there against the said Sheriffs; as also for the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of all such Sums of Money that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Collected by the said Collectors in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner aforesaid, and the other part thereof to deliver forthwith unto the High-Sheriffs of the respective Counties where such Houses or Edifices stand; And if any person or persons shall upon demand, refuse or neglect to pay the respective Sums of Money and Values, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111460:6"/> or Fines so Assest and set upon him or them for his or their respective Houses, Out-houses, or Edifices, or for his or their default, or upon his or their respective Houses, Out-houses, or Edifices, That then it shall and may be lawful to and for such Receiver or his sufficient Deputy or Deputies, for non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, to levy the same by distress of the Goods and Chattels of the person or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons so refusing or neglecting; &amp; the Distress so taken, to carry, lead or drive away, and the same to keep by the space of six days at the costs and charges of the Owner thereof; And if the said Owners do not pay the said sum of Money so Assest upon him, and due by this Act as aforesaid, within the said six days, That then the same Distress shall be apprized by three or two of the Inhabitants, where such Distress is taken, and then shall be sold by the said Collector or Collectors, for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Money so Due and Assest as aforesaid, and the overplus coming by the sale (if any be) over and above the charge of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the said Distress, to be immediately resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Owner thereof.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any person or persons shall neglect to pay such years Rent or Value, Rate, Fine, Forfeiture or Proportion, or any part thereof, as is Appointed or Assessed for him or her to pay, by and according to the tenor and true meaning of this Act, after demand to be made to such person or persons, or in his or her absence at the house or other most usual place of his or her abode or resort, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111460:7"/> no sufficient distress can or may be found to levy the same, That then it shall and may be lawful to and for the said Commissioners, or any three or more of them, by their Warrant or Warrants under their Hands and Seals dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Constables, Tithingmen, or other chief Officer or Officers of the Place where such person or persons making default dwells, to require them to apprehend such person or persons so making default as aforesaid, and to carry him or them to the common Gaol of the said County, there to lye without bail or mainprise, until they have satisfied and paid the said respective sums so Assest on him or them, with the Costs and Charges of such Constable or other Officer or Officers sustained in the apprehending and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of such person or persons. And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That for every Dwelling-house, and Out-house, or other Building Erected and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued as aforesaid, whereof no Return or Certificate is or shall be made in maner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said within six Moneths from and after the <hi>24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               </hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1657. unto the said Commission<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or to the said Parties so Authorized as aforesaid by the Tenants, Owners, or Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers, or by the Guardian of every Infant, Owner, or Tenant of such Houses as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, there shall be paid and forfeited unto His Highness the Lord Protector and His Successors, for the benefit of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, two whole years Rent, or years Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, of every such Dwelling-house, Out-house, or Building, according to the true
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111460:7"/> Value and improved Rent thereof, to be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in His Highness Court of Exchequer, against the Owner, Tenant or Tenants, and Tenants jointly or severally, of every such Dwelling-house, Out-house, or other Building, according to his and their several and respective Estates, Interest, and Proportion, by any person or persons that will sue for the same, by Bill, Informations, or Actions of Debt, wherein no Essoign, Protection, Wager of Law, Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition or License to Compound shall be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, one third part to be to the Informer, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son so suing, and the residue to His Highness the Lord Protector and His Successors, for the use of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>And be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all and every Owner and Occupier of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Houses, Edifices, Out-houses and Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, so already built and continued as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, or by this Act allowed to be built, their Heirs, Executors, Administrators and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, and all and every other person and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Bodies Politick and Corporate, which now have, or hereafter shall have any Right, Title or Interest, of, in, or to the said Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, Edifices, Out-houses and Cotages, shall from and after the payment and satisfaction of such Fine and Fines, so to be set and imposed as aforesaid, be for ever acquitted and discharged of, and from all Penalties, Forfeitures, Suits, Informations, Indictments, Prosecutions and Molestations whatsoever, by, for, or in behalf of the Commonwealth, of, for, or concerning only the Building or continuing the said Houses, Edifices, Out-houses and Cottages; And that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111460:8"/> the said Houses, Edifices, Out-houses and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, onely as to the Building and continuing thereof, shall not be (after payment as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said) adjudged publick or common Nusances, nor be subject, or be liable to be demolished or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated as such; Any Law, Statute, or Custome to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that there shall be allowed in every pound of the monies Collected as aforesaid, the sum of six pence to the Commissioners, Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Receiver, and their Deputies, Clerks, and others imployed in this service, to be paid according to these proportions following, (that is to say) to the Commissioners for their Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the sum of three pence, to the three Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters for discharge of their Salaries, the sum of one penny, to the Receiver in discharge of his Salary and pains, and the salary and pains of such Deputy or Deputies as he shall have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to imploy in this service, by the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Commissioners, or any three or more of them, the sum of one half penny, and to the Clerks which shall be assistant to the Registers and other Officers imployed by the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this service, and for all other Contingent charges, the sum of three half pence, which said Salaries shall be divided, and proportioned by the order and directions of the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or any three or more of them.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That the Receiver, before he take upon him the execution of his said Office, shall put in security to His Highness the Lord Protector, before the Barons of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, for the faithfull execution of his trust therein.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111460:8"/>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that the Commissioners hereby Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized as aforesaid, shall within six daies after the Receipt of the aforesaid Commission to them directed, meet together in some conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient place, and then and there agree to divide themselves into several Limits and Divisions, and of the manner of notice to be given to the aforesaid Owners and Tenants, and how to put this Act and the Authorities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers aforesaid in present execution.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that if any Action or Actions shall, at any time hereafter, be sued or brought against any Commissioner or Commissioners, or against any Officer or Officers, Minister or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Person or Persons, for any thing that he or they shall act or do, or cause to be done by virtue of, and according to this Act, that then every such Person or Persons so sued, shall plead the general issue, and give this Act in evidence; and if Iudgement be given for such Defendant or Defendants, that then in every such case the Defendant or Defendants so sued, shall have and recover against the Plaintiffe double Costs; Any Law to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all and every person and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, which, from and after the nine and twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth day of <hi>September,</hi> One thousand six hundred fifty seven, shall erect or new build any Dwelling house, Out-house, or Cotage, for habitation, in and upon any Lands or Tenements upon a new foundation, and shall not assign and lay four Acres of Ground, as aforesaid, at the least to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111460:9"/> every such House or Cotage, so to be erected or built, in the Suburbs of the City of <hi>London,</hi> or within ten miles of the said City, shall forfeit, lose and pay to his Highness the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and his Successors, the full and entire sum of One hundred pounds of Lawfull <hi>English</hi> money for every such Offence, and to and for the use of the Commonwealth; and every person that shall uphold and continue any such new erected House, shall forfeit to his Highness the Lord Protector and his Successors, for the use and benefit of the poor of the Parish where such Offence shall be committed, the sum of twenty pounds for every moneth, that any such House shall be upheld and continued, to be recovered by Action of Debt in any of his Highness Courts of Record within this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, wherein no Essoign, Protection or Wager of Law shall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And for the prevention of the burning and firing of Houses, and the preservation and saving of Timber for the future, Be it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that all and all manner of Houses, Edifices and Cotages hereafter to be built within the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> or the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Suburbs thereof, or within the Burrough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> upon any old or new foundation, shall be built with Brick or Stone, or both, and straight up, without butting or Iet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out into the Street, Lane or place, where such Houses, Edifices, or Cottages shall be built; And that every person &amp; persons, that shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after build or erect any House, Edifice, Out house, or Cottage, within the said Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> or the Liberties and Suburbs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111460:9"/> thereof, or within the Burough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> and doth not build the same with Brick or Stone or both, as aforesaid, straight up without Ietting or butting out, as aforesaid, every such person shall forfeit lose and pay to His Highness the Lord Protector and his Successors, the full and entire sum of One hundred pounds of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full money for every such offence, to be recovered by action of debt, in any of his Highness Courts of Record, within this Common-wealth, wherein no Essoign, Protection or wager of Law shall be allowed. Provided alwaies, that nothing herein conteyned shall extend to any Churches, Chappels, Hospitals, or Almes-houses erected or built since the said five and twentieth day of <hi>March</hi> in the year of our Lord One thousand six hundred and twenty, or which hereafter shall be built, any thing herein conteyned to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Provided that every Action to be brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any person or persons, for any offence within this Act, shall be brought and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced within one year, from and after such offence committed and not otherwise.</p>
            <p>Provided that this Act shall not extend to fine any person for his interest bought from the State, in such Houses as have been built since One thousand six hundred and twenty, upon Kings, Queens, Princes Lands, or upon Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops Lands, or Deans and Chapters Lands, or Delinquents Lands, as have been Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, and sold by Authority of Parliament, but that they shall stand and remain and receive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111460:10"/> the same benefit and advantages, as the rest within this Act, so as this Proviso shall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to free any Houses built upon the Lands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid since the purchase thereof, nor to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest or Estate in such Houses of any person who bought not nor derives the same from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies and be it Enacted, That in regard of the great charges that <hi>Francis</hi> late Earl of <hi>Bedford</hi> hath been at, in building a Church in <hi>Covent Garden</hi> in the County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex,</hi> and in the Endowments of the same Church, and other publique charges, in and about the Parish of <hi>Covent Garden</hi> aforesaid, there be abated unto <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Bedford, John Russel</hi> and <hi>Edward Russel</hi> Esqs; sons of the said <hi>Francis</hi> late Earl of <hi>Bedford,</hi> out of the Fines which shall be payable by them by force of this Act, in respect of the buildings in the said Parish of <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> the sum of seven thousand pounds, the same Abatements to be made unto them by the said Commissioners proportionably, accordingly as they shall be severally Charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by this Act, any thing to the contrary thereof, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That this Act, or any thing therein conteyned, shall not extend to any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, House or Building, that shall hereafter be built in or upon two hundred and fifty Acres of Meadow ground lying next unto the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> by the States Dock and Yard, at <hi>Deptford,</hi> purchased of Sir <hi>John Barksted</hi> and his Regiment, by <hi>Robert Stanton, Samuel Moyer,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:111460:10"/>
               <hi>Charls Harris,</hi> and others upon encouragement for the making therein Harbours and Moulds for the Riding of three Hundred Sail of Ships, without the use of Anchor or Cable, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many Conveniences shall be made for the building, Carening, and repairing many Ships together, towards which much hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended already in digging one of the Moulds and Cuts towards the others, and Contracts made for Provisions and workmanship to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great value. So as such Harbours and Moulds, be finished before the first day of <hi>July,</hi> which shall be in the year One thousand six hundred sixty and seven, and not otherwise; and so as the undertaking of this work be approved of by His Highness the Lord Protector and the Council, so as the said undertakers to within one moneth after the erecting of the said several and respective Houses or Buildings, satisfie and pay unto His Highness the Lord Protector and his Successors, one full years value of all and every the said Houses so to be built.</p>
            <p>Provided also, That nothing conteyned in this Act, shall be extended to charge either the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of <hi>Christs-Hospital, St. Batholomews-Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital, Bridewel, Thomas</hi> and <hi>Bethlehem Hospital,</hi> in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Burrough of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> for any Houses erected by them within the time aforesaid with the Poores stock, and which are for the immediate use and relief of the Poor of the same Hospitals.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That whereas there is an agreement or contract made between the society
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111460:11"/> of <hi>Lincolns-</hi>Inne, and <hi>James Cooper</hi> and <hi>Robert Henley, Esqs;</hi> and other Owners of certain par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Ground in the Fields, commonly called <hi>Lincolns</hi> Inne-Fields, for the erecting and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing certain Houses and new Buildings on three sides of the said Fields, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying and assuring the rest and residue of the said Fields unto the said society, and for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the same into Walks, for common use and benefit, whereby the great Annoyances which formerly have been to the said Fields, will be taken away, and Passengers there for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture better secured; This Act or any thing therein contained, shall not extend, or be constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to extend, to any Houses which shall at any time before the firstday of <hi>October,</hi> in the year of our Lord One thousand six hundred fifty nine, be built by the said <hi>James Cooper, Robert Henley,</hi> or other the respective Owners of the said parcels of Ground, their Heirs and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, in pursuance and according to the said Contract or Agreement, so as the said <hi>James Cooper, Robert Henley,</hi> and other the Owners aforesaid, their Heirs or Assignes, do, within one moneth after the Erecting of the said seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and respective Houses or Buildings, satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and pay unto His Highness the Lord Protector and His Successors, one full years value of all and every the said Houses so to be built, and in so doing, the said Owners, their Heirs and Assignes shall have the same benefit and advantage of this Act, as if the said Houses were already built, any Law or Statute to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111460:11"/>
            <p>Provided also, that this Act, or any thing therein contained, shall not extend to any Houses or Buildings, which shall at any time before the first day of <hi>October,</hi> in the year of Our Lord, One thousand six hundred fifty and nine, be built by <hi>Francis Finch <hi>Esq;</hi>
               </hi> his Heirs or Assignes, on his parcel of Ground in <hi>Lincolns</hi> Inne Fields, in the County of <hi>Middlesex</hi> aforesaid, so as the said <hi>Francis Finch,</hi> his Heirs or Assignes, do within one moneth after the erecting of the said several and respective Houses or Buildings, satisfie and pay unto His Highness the Lord Protector and His Successors, one full years value of all and every the said Houses so to be built, and so as neither the said <hi>Francis Finch,</hi> his Heirs nor Assignes, shall build upon any part of those Fields, which by Contract between the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> and <hi>Robert Henley</hi> Esq; <hi>James Cowper</hi> Esq; and others, are agreed to be left open and laid into Walks, for common use and benefit; And in so doing the said <hi>Francis Finch,</hi> his Heirs and Assigns shall have the same Benefit and Advantage of this Act, as if the said Houses or Buildings were already built; any Law or Statute to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <p>Provided, That this Act shall not extent to charge, tho Interest and Estate of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111460:12"/> of the Free-school in <hi>St. Olaves</hi> Parish in <hi>Southwark,</hi> or of the Poor of the said Parish, for any Houses built, or hereafter to be built, upon <hi>Horsey-Down</hi> for the use of the said Poor, before the four and twentieth of <hi>June,</hi> One thousand six hundred fifty and nine, but shall extend to charge the several Tenants of the said Houses and Buildings, for their Estates and Interests respectively.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that it shall and may be lawfull for Sir <hi>John Barkstead</hi> Knight, who did, in the year of Our Lord God, One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand six hundred fourty seven, purchase of the Trustees for sale of Bishops Lands, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of one Messuage, with the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, situate in <hi>Shoe-lane,</hi> in the Parish of <hi>Andrews Holborn,</hi> within the Suburbs of the City of <hi>London▪</hi> called <hi>Bangor-house,</hi> after a Term for Years yet unexpired, with some waste Ground thereunto belonging, conteining in length One hundred sixty eight Foot of As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>size, and in breadth, from East to West, One hundred sixty four Foot of Assize, be the same more or less, with a purpose to build thereupon at the expiration of the said Lease, the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereupon being the chief advantage he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to make by the said Purchase, and in that respect, having given much more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111460:12"/> he would have done, The said Place being at present, both dangerous and noysome to the Passengers and Inhabitants near ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning, to Erect and new Build such Messua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Tenements, and Houses thereupon, as he shall think fit. The said Sir <hi>John Barkstead,</hi> his Heirs or Assignes, paying for so much of the said Buildings, as shall be Erected upon new Foundations, unto the Receipt of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer of his Highness the Lord Protector and his Successors, to the use of his Highness and his Successors, within two moneths after such Building or Buildings Erected, One years value at an improved and full Rent.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That this Act, or any thing therein conteyned shall not hinder or be any Impediment, but the President and Governours of the Corporation for the Poor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Liberties thereof, shall or may have liberty to improve a small parcel of Ground lying within the Walls of the Work-house in the <hi>Minorites,</hi> without <hi>Algate London,</hi> belonging to the said Corporation, by Building, for the increase of the Revenue to be imployed for the Education of poor Children, and Imploying and Relieving the Poor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the said Corporation; any thing in this Act to the contrary in any wise notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:111460:13"/>
            <p>Provided alwaies, And be it further Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Authority aforesaid, in respect of the great Charge which <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Clare</hi> hath been at in erecting several new Buildings upon his Inheritance in <hi>Clements-Inn</hi> Fields, in the Parish of <hi>Clements Danes,</hi> in the County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex,</hi> usefull for an open and free Market, That from henceforth for ever hereafter, on every <hi>Tuesday, Thursday,</hi> and <hi>Saturday,</hi> in every Week, there shall be a common, open and free Market held in <hi>Clements-Inn</hi> Fields aforesaid, where the said Buildings useful for a Market are erected, and in the places near thereunto adjoining; And to enjoy all Liberties, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, Advantages, and Emoluments, inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent usually, and of right belonging and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to Markets.</p>
            <p>Provided, That this Act or any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned, shall not extend to the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing or Levying of any Fine or Penaltie upon any House or Cotage below <hi>London-bridg,</hi> and within two Furlongs of the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> which is the proper Interest of any Mariner, Ship-carpenter or Calker, whilest they or any of them, their Wives, Widowes, or Families, shall Dwell and Inhabit within the same, or whilest such Cottage or House shall remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanted: But that the said Houses and Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and every of them, for, and in respect
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111460:13"/> of the Right and Interest of the said Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Ship-Carpenters, or Calkers, their Wives or Widowes, or any of them, whilst they Retain and Inhabit the same, shall be freed and discharged from all Fines and Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by this Act Imposed, or to be Imposed, so as nothing in this Proviso extend to the benefit of any other Person or Persons, save such Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, Ship-carpenters, and Calkers, their Wives and Widowes.</p>
            <p>Provided alwaies, That whereas <hi>Edward Hall, John Hall, John Kizlingberry, Henry Sherborn, Roger Adey, Richard Tippin, John Phillips,</hi> and <hi>Mary Thomson</hi> Widow, have taken several Leases for one and fourty Years, of a certain parcel of Ground in <hi>Stanhop</hi> Street, along a dead Wall, from the end of <hi>Black-Moor</hi> Street to <hi>May-pole</hi> Lane, in the Parish of <hi>Clement Danes</hi> in the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> containing in front in the said Street Two hundred and six Foot, and in depth about sixty Foot, who in their said Leases binde themselves to build upon the said Ground substantial and strong Brick-houses, which will remove many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyances there, and make that place more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for Passengers, and have therefore dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bursed great Sums of Money, This Act or any thing therein contained shall not extend or be construed to extend to any Houses which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111460:14"/> shall at any time before the first Day of <hi>October</hi> in the Year of our Lord, One thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fifty eight, be built by the said <hi>Edward Hall, John Hall, John Kizlingberry, Henry Sherborn, Roger Adey, Richard Tippin, John Philips,</hi> and <hi>Mary Thomson,</hi> the respective Owners of the said par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Ground, so as the said <hi>Edward Hall, John Hall, John Kizlingberry, Henry Sherborn, Roger Adey, Richard Tippin, John Philips,</hi> and <hi>Mary Thomson,</hi> the Owners aforesaid, their Executors, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators or Assigns, do within one Moneth after the erecting of the said several and respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive houses or Buildings, satisfie and pay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Highness the Lord Protector, or his Successours, one full Years value of all and every the said Houses so to be built, and in so doing, the said Owners shall have the same Benefit and Advantage of this Act, as if the said houses were already built; any Law or Statute to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> and <hi>Iohn Field,</hi> Printers to His Highness the Lord PROTECTOR, 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111460:14"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>